RHYS J. SMOKER

Bellingham, WA

Phone: 907 209 8448| Email: merning.the.midnight.oil@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/rhys-smoker/

Web applications Portfolio: https://MERN-ing-the-midnight-oil.github.io/Portfolio-with-React/

Code Repositories: https://github.com/MERN-ing-the-midnight-oil

SUMMARY

With a background rooted in education and hands-on experience with government agencies and nonprofits, I am a well-rounded professional committed to driving positive change. My training in web development positions me to effectively use technology to creatively support the passions of people and agencies working to help others.

EDUCATION

• Full Stack Web Development Certificate

University of Washington, Seattle, WA

Master of Arts in Teaching

University of Alaska Southeast, Juneau AK

Bachelor of Science in Oceanography

Cal Poly Humboldt, Arcata, CA

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Front-End Development: HTML/CSS, Advanced CSS, React.js, Material UI, Bootstrap, jQuery, jQuery UI, Responsive Design, CSS Variables, Pseudo-Classes and Pseudo-Elements in CSS, CSS Resets, CSS Frameworks (including Google Fonts), JavaScript (ES6+ Syntax), TypeScript, Wireframing, Formik.
- Back-End Development: Node.js, Express.js, RESTful API Design, GraphQL, Server-Side APIs, Authentication, Sequelize, JSON Web Tokens (JWT).
- Database Management: SQL, NoSQL, MongoDB Compass, IndexedDB.
- **Programming Concepts:** Object-Oriented Programming (OOP), Test-Driven Development, Model-View-Controller (MVC), Algorithms and Data Structures, Functional Programming.
- **Development Tools:** Git Version Control, GitHub, Insomnia, Command Line Usage, Workbox, Service Workers.
- **Web Technologies:** Web APIs, Third-Party APIs, Progressive Web Applications (PWA), Client-Side Storage.

• Frameworks and Libraries: MERN Stack (MongoDB, Express.js, React, Node.js), Redux, Moment.js.

EXPERIENCE

FULL STACK WEB DEVELOPER, UNIV. WASHINGTON, (GRADUATED MARCH 2023)

Six month certificate program with the school of continuing education designed to provide understanding of the essentials of web development using the MERN stack. Lecture and in-class exercises for a total of 240 class hours with an additional 720 hours of expected out of class study and homework.

EDUCATOR, BELLINGHAM PUBLIC SCHOOL DISTRICT, WASHINGTON, 2016-2022

- Designed and taught Marine Ecology, Game Design, Coding, Robotics, Pre-Algebra, Astronomy, Neurobiology, Agricultural Economics, and other courses at Explorations Academy.
- Organized and co-led field orientations, backcountry camping trips, and field learning intensives.
- Served in an advising role with individual students (academic, personal, and career counseling).
- Worked one on one and in small groups giving support to students needing IEP services and behavioral supports in general ed. settings at Fairhaven Middle School.
- Substitute teacher for over 100 classrooms.

AGENT, DEPT OF EDUCATION & DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION, JUNEAU, 2010-2015

- Processed DOT driveway and encroachment permits and assisted with land acquisition.
- Led public informational sessions on DOT highway improvement projects and contacted the public to resolve right of way encroachment issues.
- Suggested, developed, and implemented a Keyhole Markup Language (KML) system to map paper-based driveway permit data to the precise geographic locations of driveways.
- Received "employee of the quarter" award from the Alaska Commision on Postsecondary Education in 2014.
- Counseled college students applying for or receiving loans, grants, and scholarships.

• Reset Passwords and did troubleshooting for users of the Alaska Student Aid portal.

EDUCATOR, JUNEAU SCHOOL DISTRICT, 2007-2011

- Taught Middle School Science and Math at Dzantik'i Heeni Middle School, Juneau AK.
- Student-taught Oceanography and Biology at Juneau Douglas High School.
- One on one paraeducator support for special education students at Riverbend Elementary.

FISHERIES SCIENCE, NMFS/NOAA, 1999-2007

- Field Research assistant (Ecosystems, social-ecological systems, and culture: Using systems perspectives to inform fisheries management in the Pribilof Islands, Alaska.)"
- Laboratory technician at NMFS fisheries genetics laboratory, Auke Bay Marine Lab, Juneau, AK.
- Research Vessel Valero: Conducted a five-day internship with a multibeam swath mapping survey in the Channel Islands with Oregon State University's Active Tectonics Group (Nov 2005).
- Research Vessel Coral Sea: Completed sixty hours assisting with class projects, including CTD profiling, hydrocasts, box cores, and plankton tows with Humboldt State University (Fall 2000-Spring 2005).
- Research Vessel Miller Freeman: Undertook a three-week internship in the Gulf of Alaska on a NOAA ship for a GLOBEC Juvenile Salmon Survey, supervising tucker trawls, assisting with CTD rosette casts, and analyzing salmon samples.
- Research Vessel John N. Cobb: Participated in a seventeen-day Southeast Alaska Coastal Monitoring cruise in Southeast Alaska, measuring and analyzing trawl-caught fish, assisting with plankton sampling, and other related tasks.

LINKS TO WRITTEN RECOMMENDATIONS

John Young (University of Washington Bootcamp Primary Instructor)

<u>James Bacchus Taylor</u> (Head of School, Explorations Academy)

<u>Jasleen Aulaakh</u> (Teacher, Fairhaven Middle School)

<u>Jessica Finstuen</u> (Teacher, Fairhaven Middle School)

AWARDS/ENDORSEMENTS

Award of Excellence

Cal Poly Humboldt's English Dept for a perfect score on a graduation writing portfolio.

Recognition of Excellence Award

PRAXIS/ETS Elementary Education: Content Knowledge.

Washington State Teaching Certificate Endorsements

English/Language Arts, Social Studies, Middle Level Mathematics, Elementary (k-8).